hey everyone i'm bradford with the penny
pictures guide to personal finance did
you know that the average american is
spending 136 dollars a month on car
insurance but that's just the average if
you're paying much more than that then
you're probably overpaying by hundreds
if not thousands of dollars each year so
let's break down eight simple strategies
that you can use to save on your auto
insurance strategy one on this list is
that you need to shop around for
different insurance companies be honest
with yourself when was the last time you
actually looked at your current coverage
and compared it to different options out
there
if you haven't you've probably left a
lot of money on the table and now is the
time to change that there are a lot of
different apps and websites that you can
just import your current coverage from
your current insurance company and then
it will instantly compare that across a
wide variety of different insurers so
you can figure out if you're actually
getting the best deal now if you don't
feel like doing the research yourself
you can always just go to an insurance
broker who's going to do that on your
behalf and their entire job is to take
what sort of coverage you want and then
they're going to go around to a bunch of
different insurance companies and try to
negotiate the best deal now a word of
caution on doing this is just because
you're getting the cheapest insurance
quote from a company doesn't mean it's
actually going to save you the most
money
make sure you're looking into different
customer reviews for that specific
company and understanding what the
company does when it's time to actually
pay out an insurance claim if the
company has a track record of making it
nearly impossible to pay out anything
then you're better off looking elsewhere
and never underestimate your power as a
potential customer all the different
insurance companies want you and your
money so they're willing to negotiate if
you actually try to give you the best
price so that way you're going to choose
their company over a different insurer
number two on this list is to just
increase your current deductible which
is the amount that you're going to have
to cover before the insurance company is
actually going to kick in to pay
anything above that amount now
increasing your deductible is one of the
easiest ways to lower your premium
without having to do any sort of
research or basically do anything
outside of your current company that you
have now the standard deductible that
most people have is going to range
anywhere from 250 on the lowest end all
the way up to a couple thousand dollars
if they're deciding to self-insure and
the reason you're going to want to have
to look into actually increasing your
deductible anywhere from 500 to a
thousand dollars up to whatever you
decide is that because you're offering
to cover more up money up front the
insurance company is going to be able to
give you a lower premium now you might
save a ton of money by doing this but on
the other hand it might only make a
small difference so how do you decide
whether it makes financial sense to
increase your insurance deductible just
do this simple test so you're going to
increase your deductible from 500 up to
a thousand dollars
see how much money you're actually going
to save with your premium over the
course of that year
if you're going to save more money in
one year with your premium being reduced
then the amount that you're actually
increasing your deductible by then it is
a good decision to increase your
deductible now if it's going to be less
than that it's probably better to just
stick with your current deductible
because the thinking is is that if you
can cover that in a year that's probably
a pretty safe timeline where you can
almost guarantee that you're not gonna
have an accident or theft or anything
like that now if the coverage time to be
able to recoup that difference in your
deductible is going to take much longer
than a year you're putting yourself at
an increased risk that you're going to
have to actually shell out more money in
the event of an accident or theft then
you're actually saving money by having
that lower premium but the caveat to all
this is that you have to have an
emergency fund in place so you can
actually afford to cover the difference
of the increased deductible that you're
putting in place number three is to stop
paying for the insurance that you don't
need if you're driving around with a
vehicle that doesn't have a very high
value say it's a couple thousand dollars
you normally consider a clunker or a
beater car then you probably don't need
to have collision or comprehensive
insurance which is insurance is going to
go towards replacing the value of your
vehicle now you can probably save a
pretty good amount in your premiums by
removing that coverage and just deciding
to self-insure instead going back to the
point that you need an emergency fund in
place but even if you don't have a very
large one you can probably just take the
difference in the premium that you're
saving and start putting that money
towards a car replacement or car repair
fund
strategy four is consider how your
vehicle looks to the insurance company
how much does your car currently cost
what type of vehicle is it the more
expensive a vehicle and the more sporty
your vehicle is is going to mean that
that vehicle costs more to insure for
the company the more expensive it costs
is pretty simple if you have a hundred
thousand dollar car it costs a lot more
to replace than if you have a 20 000 car
and the insurance company is going to
charge you for it at the same time if
you're just driving around in a minivan
you're probably not as much of a risk to
be zipping around speeding through red
lights and at a high risk of an accident
than if you're driving around in a brand
new corvette so with this in mind you
might need to consider downsizing your
super expensive sports car that you
currently have to something that is less
expensive and more boring and the same
rule applies that when it comes time to
actually buy a vehicle
take a moment to consider how the
vehicle is going to look to your
insurance company if saving as much
money on your premium as possible is
important to you number five is consider
what sort of safety and security
features your vehicle comes with
if you can make sure that your company
knows that you have side air bags that
you have emergency braking that you have
an anti-theft device in your vehicle
all those things go towards decreasing
the liability that you pose towards the
insurance company and you will be
rewarded by having a lower premium to
pay so consider adding or installing an
anti-theft device or when you're going
to buy a new vehicle check out what sort
of security features are on the vehicle
and then what various security features
and safety features your insurance
company will actually decrease your
premium for just things to think about
when you're moving forward number six
and this one should go without saying
but drive safer drive slower if you have
a bunch of speeding tickets if you're a
bunch of at fault accidents all these
things are things that are going to make
you much more of a liability and a risk
for the insurance company and they're
going to charge you for it the riskier
you are the more you're going to have to
pay so drive slower be more of a
defensive driver and make sure that
you're doing everything you can to get
from destination a to b safely and the
byproduct of being a safe and a good
driver is that you're less of an
insurance risk and your premiums are
going to go down for it and another
thing in the same vein to look into is
see if your insurance company offers any
sort of app or tracker that you can put
in your vehicle that is going to measure
your driving habits my wife and i use an
app through our auto insurance and it
tracks how fast are we driving are we
using our phone while we're driving do
we have a lot of sharp accelerations and
quick stops so how we're not really
paying attention we're having to slam on
the brakes all the time and then it
measures all that together and it gives
us a discount for being good drivers now
our discount comes out on average
between 20 and 30 percent and that's
something that's worth it to us to be
able to sacrifice some of our privacy by
giving some more information about our
habits to our auto insurance company now
i understand privacy is a really
important thing to a lot of people but
in this situation it's just going to
come down to what you value more having
a lower premium or having more of your
privacy number seven on this list is
just ask ask your insurance company what
sort of discounts they offer and have an
insurance agent go through all the
different discounts and see if you
qualify for them whether it's a
multi-car coverage discount whether it
is a length of membership with that
specific insurance company and getting a
discount from that good driver discounts
if you have a young child or a teenager
that's driving or do they offer good
student discounts ask for anything and
everything because the worst that they
can say is just no there are a lot of
various small discounts out there that
can really add up over time but you're
never going to get them if you don't ask
in the first place and finally number
eight on this list is improve your
credit score now i know
what the heck does your credit score
have to do with you as a driver
but the reality of it is is that there
are a lot of car insurance companies
that will look at your credit score and
use that to help measure the risk and in
turn how much you pay as a premium for
your car insurance the higher your
credit score the lower your premium the
lower your credit score the higher your
premium
now whether or not this makes sense and
i don't really think it does or that
it's necessarily fair but that's how it
is so you want to make sure you have the
highest credit score possible so that
way you're paying the lowest in premiums
now if you're trying to figure out ways
that you can actually increase your
credit score or how it just works check
out this video here
and i want to thank you for watching
with me today and please remember from
your first penny to your first million
we're here to help